Action Example

action_example.info

   1 name = Action example
   2 description = Demonstrates providing actions that can be associated to triggers.
   3 package = Example modules
   4 core = 7.x
   5 dependencies[] = trigger
   6 files[] = action_example.test

action_example.module

  1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Action definition example module.
   6  */
   7 
   8 /**
   9  * @defgroup action_example Example: Action
  10  * @ingroup examples
  11  * @{
  12  * Creating actions in Drupal 7
  13  *
  14  * Triggers and actions are a matched pair of Drupal features allowing some
  15  * Drupal programming without using PHP. Using the appropriate action in a
  16  * specific event, a site administrator can add new functionality.
  17  *
  18  * Examples are:
  19  *  - Send an email after a node is published or edited.
  20  *  - Display a message after a user has logged in.
  21  *  - Display a message and send an email after a node has been deleted.
  22  *
  23  * A trigger is a special function which can enqueue actions. The trigger module
  24  * provides the interface allowing us to associate certain actions with certain
  25  * triggers.
  26  *
  27  * Actions are the functions designed to be run by triggers.
  28  *
  29  * A trigger should build the appropriate context for the action to be fired.
  30  * Actions are very often grouped by functionality: examples are 'user', 'node',
  31  * 'taxonomy'. When actions are grouped it is because they expect the same
  32  * arguments. This way, you can enqueue as many actions understanding the 'user'
  33  * object as you want.
  34  *
  35  * Not all actions can be used in all triggers because they require different
  36  * contexts. But some actions are generic enough that they do not require
  37  * special objects in their contexts, and so can be used on every available
  38  * trigger. This 'group' type is used by actions to be available for this
  39  * trigger.
  40  *
  41  * What are good candidates to be triggers? Any function can be a trigger, as
  42  * long as it has the code to call the enqueued actions, but to make Drupal
  43  * more extensible, you will find hooks (from Drupal and contributed modules)
  44  * very good candidates. A trigger should build the arguments, ask for enqueued
  45  * actions and run them. You may define a function being a trigger, and run it
  46  * through a button in the front page, or you may prepare a trigger for a hook,
  47  * and everytime that hook is fired, your trigger will be.
  48  *
  49  * What are good candidates to be actions? any function is a possible action,
  50  * the only problem is finding a trigger able to run it.
  51  *
  52  * This module describes how to create actions for Drupal. In this
  53  * example we are providing three actions:
  54  *
  55  * - A generic action that can be used in any trigger, which is the most
  56  *   basic example of an action.
  57  *
  58  * - An action which which extends the capabilities of User triggers, even if
  59  *   associated with node or comment events.
  60  *
  61  * - An action which extends the capabilities of node triggers, but limited
  62  *   to certain events only, and using a customizable option.
  63  *
  64  * @see trigger_example
  65  * @see hook_action_info()
  66  * @see @link http://drupal.org/node/172152 Writing Actions in Drupal 6 @endlink
  67  * @see @link http://drupal.org/node/199254 Triggers and Actions in Drupal 6 @endlink
  68  */
  69 
  70 /**
  71  * Implements hook_action_info().
  72  *
  73  * We call hook_action_info when we are defining the actions we provide.
  74  * Actions are the actions fired by the associated triggers. In this example,
  75  * we are registering our three new actions, providing the unique name (using
  76  * Drupal's convention modulename_description_action), an easy to understand
  77  * description of what the action does, the 'object' expected by this action
  78  * (default options from core are node, user, comment and system, however other
  79  * trigger modules may declare new object types), which are the triggers allowed
  80  * to use these action, and if some customization is available. Please, note
  81  * that the function name is not required to finish as _action to be declared as
  82  * a Drupal action, and that only information provided by hook_trigger_info()
  83  * will be considered for valid actions creation.
  84  *
  85  * These are the actions being provided in hook_action_info()
  86  *
  87  * - action_example_basic_action: this action is a dummy function which can be
  88  *   used by any trigger. The label describes that the action will do nothing,
  89  *   but is enough for a basic example. Type is set to system, so users will not
  90  *   be confused about the scope of this action (expecting a node, user, or any
  91  *   other object). This action is not configurable, and will appear as
  92  *   available in the list of action under the menu entry:
  93  *   'admin/config/system/actions.
  94  * - action_example_unblock_user_action: Unblocks a user.
  95  * - action_example_node_sticky_action: This action is a complex action that is
  96  *   only available to Node type triggers, and can only be associated with the
  97  *   events node presave, node insert and node update. The action does not
  98  *   exist by default and it has to be created by user configuration. This makes
  99  *   it an "advanced action" in Drupal, so-called because it requires
 100  *   configuration or customization.
 101  *   In this example action, the action will promote nodes and make them sticky
 102  *   during presave, insert, or update, but only for particular users. As an
 103  *   advanced action, it first needs to be created in the actions management
 104  *   page (admin/config/system/actions). At the bottom of that page a selection
 105  *   list shows a list of advanced actions that will includes the option
 106  *   'Promote to frontpage and sticky on top any content created by :'
 107  *   Selecting this option and clicking the 'Create' button, a configuration
 108  *   form will ask for an author name. When this action is associated to any
 109  *   of the possible Node trigger events, it will only be effective if the
 110  *   author of the content matches the author configured by the action.
 111  *
 112  * @return
 113  *   An associative array of action descriptions. The keys of the array
 114  *   are the names of the action functions, and each corresponding value
 115  *   is an associative array with the following key-value pairs:
 116  *   - 'type': The type of object this action acts upon. Core actions have types
 117  *     'node', 'user', 'comment', and 'system', but additional types can be
 118  *     used, as long as the trigger and action agree on them.
 119  *   - 'label': The human-readable name of the action, which should be passed
 120  *     through the t() function for translation.
 121  *   - 'configurable': If FALSE, then the action doesn't require any extra
 122  *     configuration. If TRUE, then your module must define a form function with
 123  *     the same name as the action function with '_form' appended (e.g., the
 124  *     form for 'node_assign_owner_action' is 'node_assign_owner_action_form'.)
 125  *     This function takes $context as its only parameter, and is paired with
 126  *     the usual _submit function, and possibly an _validate function.
 127  *   - 'triggers': An array of the triggers that can trigger this
 128  *     action. For example: array('node_insert', 'user_update'). You can also
 129  *     declare support for any trigger by returning array('any') for this value.
 130  *   - 'behavior': (optional) A machine-readable array of behaviors of this
 131  *     action, used to signal additionally required actions that may need to be
 132  *     triggered. Currently recognized behaviors by Trigger module:
 133  *     - 'changes_property': If an action with this behavior is assigned to a
 134  *       trigger other than a "presave" hook, any save actions also assigned to
 135  *       this trigger are moved later in the list. If no save action is present,
 136  *       one will be added.
 137  *       Modules that are processing actions (like Trigger module) should take
 138  *       special care in the "presave" hook, in which case a dependent "save"
 139  *       action should NOT be invoked.
 140  *
 141  * @see hook_action_info()
 142  */
 143 function action_example_action_info() {
 144   return array(
 145     'action_example_basic_action' => array(
 146       'label' => t('Action Example: A basic example action that does nothing'),
 147       'type' => 'system',
 148       'configurable' => FALSE,
 149       'triggers' => array('any'),
 150     ),
 151     'action_example_unblock_user_action' => array(
 152       'label' => t('Action Example: Unblock a user'),
 153       'type' => 'user',
 154       'configurable' => FALSE,
 155       'triggers' => array('any'),
 156     ),
 157     'action_example_node_sticky_action' => array(
 158       'type' => 'node',
 159       'label' => t('Action Example: Promote to frontpage and sticky on top any content created by :'),
 160       'configurable' => TRUE,
 161       'behavior' => array('changes_property'),
 162       'triggers' => array('node_presave', 'node_insert', 'node_update'),
 163     ),
 164   );
 165 }
 166 
 167 
 168 
 169 /**
 170  * Implements hook_menu().
 171  *
 172  * Provides a menu entry which explains what the module does.
 173  */
 174 function action_example_menu() {
 175   $items['examples/action_example'] = array(
 176     'title'           => 'Action Example',
 177     'description'     => 'Provides a basic information page.',
 178     'page callback'   => '_action_example_page',
 179     'access callback' => TRUE,
 180   );
 181   return $items;
 182 }
 183 
 184 
 185 /**
 186  * A simple page to explain to the developer what to do.
 187  */
 188 function _action_example_page() {
 189   return t("The Action Example provides three example actions which can be configured on the <a href='@actions_url'>Actions configuration page</a> and assigned to triggers on the <a href='@triggers_url'>Triggers configuration page</a>.", array('@actions_url' => url('admin/config/system/actions'), '@triggers_url' => url('admin/structure/trigger/node')));
 190 }
 191 
 192 /**
 193  * Action function for action_example_basic_action.
 194  *
 195  * This action is not expecting any type of entity object, and can be used with
 196  * any trigger type or any event.
 197  *
 198  * @param $entity
 199  *   An optional entity object.
 200  * @param $context
 201  *   Array with parameters for this action: depends on the trigger.
 202  *
 203  * @see action_example_action_info()
 204  */
 205 function action_example_basic_action(&$entity, $context = array()) {
 206   //
 207   // In this case we are ignoring the entity and the context. This case of
 208   // action is useful when your action does not depend on the context, and
 209   // the function must do something regardless the scope of the trigger.
 210   // Simply announces that the action was executed using a message.
 211 
 212   drupal_set_message(t('action_example_basic_action fired'));
 213   watchdog('action_example', 'action_example_basic_action fired.');
 214 }
 215 
 216 /**
 217  * Action function for action_example_unblock_user_action.
 218  *
 219  * This action is expecting an entity object user, node or comment. If none of
 220  * the above is provided (because it was not called from an user/node/comment
 221  * trigger event, then the action will be taken on the current logged in user.
 222  *
 223  * Unblock an user. This action can be fired from different trigger types:
 224  * - User trigger: this user will be unblocked.
 225  * - Node/Comment trigger: the author of the node or comment will be unblocked.
 226  * - Other: (including system or custom defined types), current user will be
 227  *   unblocked. (Yes, this seems like an incomprehensible use-case.)
 228  *
 229  * @param $entity
 230  *   An optional user object (could be a user, or an author if context is
 231  *   node or comment)
 232  * @param $context
 233  *   Array with parameters for this action: depends on the trigger. The context
 234  *   is not used in this example.
 235  */
 236 function action_example_unblock_user_action(&$entity, $context = array()) {
 237 
 238   // First we check that entity is a user object. If this is the case, then this
 239   // is a user-type trigger.
 240   if (isset($entity->uid)) {
 241     $uid = $entity->uid;
 242   }
 243   elseif (isset($context['uid'])) {
 244     $uid = $context['uid'];
 245   }
 246   // If neither of those are valid, then block the current user.
 247   else {
 248     $uid = $GLOBALS['user']->uid;
 249   }
 250   $account = user_load($uid);
 251   $account = user_save($account, array('status' => 1));
 252   watchdog('action_example', 'Unblocked user %name.', array('%name' => $account->name));
 253   drupal_set_message(t('Unblocked user %name', array('%name' => $account->name)));
 254 }
 255 
 256 /**
 257  * Form function for action_example_node_sticky_action.
 258  *
 259  * Since we defined action_example_node_sticky_action as 'configurable' => TRUE,
 260  * this action requires a configuration form to create/configure the action.
 261  * In this circumstance, Drupal will attempt to call a function named by
 262  * combining the action name (action_example_node_sticky_action) and _form, in
 263  * this case yielding action_example_node_sticky_action_form.
 264  *
 265  * In Drupal, actions requiring creation and configuration are called 'advanced
 266  * actions', because they must be customized to define their functionality.
 267  *
 268  * The 'action_example_node_sticky_action' allows creating rules to promote and
 269  * set sticky content created by selected users on certain events. A form is
 270  * used to configure which user is affected by this action, and this form
 271  * includes the standard _validate and _submit hooks.
 272  */
 273 
 274 
 275 /**
 276  * Generates settings form for action_example_node_sticky_action().
 277  *
 278  * @param $context
 279  *   An array of options of this action (in case it is being edited)
 280  *
 281  * @return array $form
 282  *
 283  * @see action_example_action_info()
 284  */
 285 function action_example_node_sticky_action_form($context) {
 286   /*
 287   * We return a configuration form to set the requirements that will
 288   * match this action before being executed. This is a regular Drupal form and
 289   * may include any type of information you want, but all the fields of the
 290   * form will be saved into the $context variable.
 291   *
 292   * In this case we are promoting all content types submitted by this user, but
 293   * it is possible to extend these conditions providing more options in the
 294   * settings form.
 295   */
 296   $form['author'] = array(
 297     '#title' => t('Author name'),
 298     '#type' => 'textfield',
 299     '#description' => t('Any content created, presaved or updated by this user will be promoted to front page and set as sticky.'),
 300     '#default_value' => isset($context['author']) ? $context['author'] : '',
 301   );
 302   // Verify user permissions and provide an easier way to fill this field.
 303   if (user_access('access user profiles')) {
 304     $form['author']['#autocomplete_path'] = 'user/autocomplete';
 305   }
 306   // No more options, return the form.
 307   return $form;
 308 }
 309 
 310 /**
 311  * Validates settings form for action_example_node_sticky_action().
 312  * Verifies that user exists before continuing.
 313  */
 314 function action_example_node_sticky_action_validate($form, $form_state) {
 315   if (! $account = user_load_by_name($form_state['values']['author']) ) {
 316     form_set_error('author', t('Please, provide a valid username'));
 317   }
 318 }
 319 
 320 /**
 321  * Submit handler for action_example_node_sticky_action.
 322  *
 323  * Returns an associative array of values which will be available in the
 324  * $context when an action is executed.
 325  */
 326 function action_example_node_sticky_action_submit($form, $form_state) {
 327   return array('author' => $form_state['values']['author']);
 328 }
 329 
 330 /**
 331  * Action function for action_example_node_sticky_action.
 332  *
 333  * Promote and set sticky flag. This is the special action that has been
 334  * customized using the configuration form, validated with the validation
 335  * function, and submitted with the submit function.
 336  *
 337  * @param $node
 338  *   A node object provided by the associated trigger.
 339  * @param $context
 340  *   Array with the following elements:
 341  *   - 'author': username of the author's content this function will promote and
 342  *     set as sticky.
 343  */
 344 function action_example_node_sticky_action($node, $context) {
 345   if (function_exists('dsm')) {
 346     dsm($node, 'action_example_node_sticky_action is firing. Here is the $node');
 347     dsm($context, 'action_example_node_sticky_action is firing. Here is the $context');
 348   }
 349   // Get the user configured for this special action.
 350   $account = user_load_by_name($context['author']);
 351   // Is the node created by this user? then promote and set as sticky.
 352   if ($account->uid == $node->uid) {
 353     $node->promote = NODE_PROMOTED;
 354     $node->sticky  = NODE_STICKY;
 355     watchdog('action', 'Set @type %title to sticky and promoted by special action for user %username.', array('@type' => node_type_get_name($node), '%title' => $node->title, '%username' => $account->name));
 356     drupal_set_message(t('Set @type %title to sticky and promoted by special action for user %username.', array('@type' => node_type_get_name($node), '%title' => $node->title, '%username' => $account->name)));
 357   }
 358 }
 359 /**
 360  * @} End of "defgroup action_example".
 361  */

action_example.test

   1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * test file for action_example module.
   6  */
   7 
   8 /**
   9  * Default test case for the action_example module.
  10  */
  11 class ActionExampleTestCase extends TriggerWebTestCase {
  12 
  13   public static function getInfo() {
  14     return array(
  15       'name' => 'Action example',
  16       'description' => 'Perform various tests on action_example module.' ,
  17       'group' => 'Examples',
  18     );
  19   }
  20 
  21   function setUp() {
  22     parent::setUp('trigger', 'action_example');
  23   }
  24 
  25  /**
  26    * Test Action Example.
  27    *
  28    * 1. action_example_basic_action: Configure a action_example_basic_action to
  29    *    happen when user logs in.
  30    * 2. action_example_unblock_user_action: When a user's profile is being
  31    *    viewed, unblock that user.
  32    * 3. action_example_node_sticky_action: Create a user, configure that user
  33    *    to always be stickied using advanced configuration. Have the user
  34    *    create content; verify that it gets stickied.
  35    */
  36   function testActionExample() {
  37     // Create an administrative user.
  38     $admin_user = $this->drupalCreateUser(array('administer actions', 'access comments', 'access content', 'post comments', 'skip comment approval', 'create article content', 'access user profiles', 'administer users'));
  39     $this->drupalLogin($admin_user);
  40 
  41     // 1. Assign basic action; then logout and login user and see if it puts
  42     // the message on the screen.
  43     $hash = drupal_hash_base64('action_example_basic_action');
  44     $edit = array('aid' => $hash);
  45     $this->drupalPost('admin/structure/trigger/user', $edit, t('Assign'), array(), array(), 'trigger-user-login-assign-form');
  46 
  47     $this->drupalLogout();
  48     $this->drupalLogin($admin_user);
  49     $this->assertText(t('action_example_basic_action fired'));
  50 
  51     // 2. Unblock: When a user's profile is being viewed, unblock.
  52     $normal_user = $this->drupalCreateUser();
  53     user_save($normal_user, array('status' => 0));  // Blocked user.
  54     $normal_user = user_load($normal_user->uid, TRUE);
  55     $this->assertFalse($normal_user->status, 'Normal user status has been set to blocked');
  56 
  57     $hash = drupal_hash_base64('action_example_unblock_user_action');
  58     $edit = array('aid' => $hash);
  59     $this->drupalPost('admin/structure/trigger/user', $edit, t('Assign'), array(), array(), 'trigger-user-view-assign-form');
  60 
  61     $this->drupalGet("user/$normal_user->uid");
  62     $normal_user = user_load($normal_user->uid, TRUE);
  63     $this->assertTrue($normal_user->status, 'Normal user status has been set to unblocked');
  64     $this->assertRaw(t('Unblocked user %name', array('%name' => $normal_user->name)));
  65 
  66     // 3. Create a user whose posts are always to be stickied.
  67     $sticky_user = $this->drupalCreateUser(array('access comments', 'access content', 'post comments', 'skip comment approval', 'create article content'));
  68 
  69     $action_label = $this->randomName();
  70     $edit = array(
  71       'actions_label' => $action_label,
  72       'author' => $sticky_user -> name,
  73     );
  74     $aid = $this->configureAdvancedAction('action_example_node_sticky_action', $edit);
  75     $edit = array('aid' => drupal_hash_base64($aid));
  76     $this->drupalPost('admin/structure/trigger/node', $edit, t('Assign'), array(), array(), 'trigger-node-insert-assign-form');
  77     // Now create a node and verify that it gets stickied.
  78     $this->drupalLogout();
  79     $this->drupalLogin($sticky_user);
  80     $node = $this->drupalCreateNode();
  81     $this->assertTrue($node->sticky, 'Node was set to sticky on creation');
  82   }
  83 }

Dynamically Typed

No need to explicitly declare type

Strongly Typed

The interpreter will not accept jokes like adding char to an integer type.

1 + a  (will not work)

Immutability

Once you give data a type, it has that type forever.

a - 3.14
a = int(a) --> will work
b = int(a) --> will not work

Evaluation Strategy

Call by value

The argument expression is evaluated, and the resulting value is bound to the corresponding variable in the function (frequently by copying the value into a new memory region). Separation of data in terms of outside the function and inside the function. foo(a): when a is passed to foo, a new copy is created.

function operates on a copy of the passed-in arguments

Call by reference

Function receives an implicit reference to the argument, rather than a copy of its value. In case of foo(a): data being passed here is the same data as being modified by the function.

function operates on the original outside arguments

Call by reference has the advantage of greater time and space efficiency (since arguments do not need to be copied).

Python - Call by Sharing (Call by object-sharing)

The semantics of call by sharing differ from call by reference in that assignments to function arguments within the function are not visible to the caller. However, since the function has access to the same object as the caller (no copy is made), mutations to those objects within the function are visible to the caller, which differs from call by value. Strings are immutable.

If an argument value is a mutable object, Python uses call by reference.
If an argument value is immutable, Python uses call by value.

#!/usr/bin/python

# Function definition is here
def changeme (mylist):
    "This changes a passed list into this function"
    mylist.append([1,2,3,4]);
    print "Values inside the function: ", mylist
    return

# Now you can call changeme function
mylist = [10,20,30];
changeme(mylist);
print("Values outside the function: ", mylist)

Values inside the function:  [10, 20, 30, [1, 2, 3, 4]]
Values outside the function:  [10, 20, 30, [1, 2, 3, 4]]

Contextual Links Example

contextual-links-example-object.tpl.php

   1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Default theme implementation to display a sample object with contextual links.
   6  *
   7  * Available variables:
   8  * - $title: The sanitized title of the object.
   9  * - $content: The sanitized content of the object.
  10  * These are defined in template_preprocess_contextual_links_example_object()
  11  * and represent whichever variables you might actually use to display the
  12  * main content of your module's object.
  13  *
  14  * Standard variables (required for contextual links):
  15  * - $classes: String of classes that can be used to style contextually through
  16  *   CSS.
  17  * - $title_prefix (array): An array containing additional output populated by
  18  *   modules, intended to be displayed in front of the main title tag that
  19  *   appears in the template.
  20  * - $title_suffix (array): An array containing additional output populated by
  21  *   modules, intended to be displayed after the main title tag that appears in
  22  *   the template.
  23  * The above variables are a subset of those which Drupal provides to all
  24  * templates, and they must be printed in your template file in order for
  25  * contextual links to be properly attached. For example, the core Contextual
  26  * Links module adds the renderable contextual links themselves inside
  27  * $title_suffix, so they will appear immediately after the object's title in
  28  * the HTML. (This placement is for accessibility reasons, among others.)
  29  */
  30 ?>
  31 <div class="<?php print $classes; ?>">
  32   <?php print render($title_prefix); ?>
  33   <h2><?php print $title; ?></h2>
  34   <?php print render($title_suffix); ?>
  35   <?php print $content; ?>
  36 </div>

contextual_links_example.info

   1 name = Contextual links example
   2 description = Demonstrates how to use contextual links for enhancing the user experience.
   3 package = Example modules
   4 core = 7.x
   5 files[] = contextual_links_example.test

contextual_links_example.module

   1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Shows how to use Drupal's contextual links functionality.
   6  *
   7  * @see http://drupal.org/node/1089922
   8  */
   9 
  10 /**
  11  * @defgroup contextual_links_example Example: Contextual Links
  12  * @ingroup examples
  13  * @{
  14  * Example of implementing contextual links.
  15  */
  16 
  17 /**
  18  * Implements hook_menu().
  19  *
  20  * Drupal's menu system allows you to indicate that particular menu items
  21  * should be displayed as contextual links. If you hover over a block or node
  22  * while logged in as an administrator (and with the Contextual Links module
  23  * enabled) you'll see a small gear icon appear. Click on this icon, and the
  24  * list of items that appears in the exposed menu are what Drupal calls
  25  * "contextual links".
  26  *
  27  * Contextual links allow site administrators to quickly perform actions
  28  * related to elements on a page, without having to hunt through the
  29  * administrative interface. As such, you should usually attach them to objects
  30  * that appear on the main part of a Drupal site and limit them to a few common
  31  * tasks that are frequently performed (for example, "edit" or "configure").
  32  * Do not rely on contextual links being present for your module to work
  33  * correctly, since they are a convenience feature only. Within Drupal core,
  34  * the Contextual Links module must be enabled (and the user viewing the page
  35  * must have the "access contextual links" permission) in order for the
  36  * contextual links corresponding to actions that the user can perform to
  37  * actually be injected into the page's HTML.
  38  *
  39  * Three examples of contextual links are provided here. Although none are
  40  * difficult to implement, they are presented in order of increasing
  41  * complexity:
  42  * - Attaching contextual links to a node.
  43  * - Attaching contextual links to a block.
  44  * - Attaching contextual links to an arbitrary piece of content defined by
  45  *   your module.
  46  *
  47  * @see contextual_links_example_block_info()
  48  * @see contextual_links_example_block_view()
  49  * @see contextual_links_overview_page()
  50  */
  51 function contextual_links_example_menu() {
  52   // First example (attaching contextual links to a node):
  53   //
  54   // Many modules add tabs to nodes underneath the node/<nid> path. If the path
  55   // you are adding corresponds to a commonly performed action on the node, you
  56   // can choose to expose it as a contextual link. Since the Node module
  57   // already has code to display all contextual links underneath the node/<nid>
  58   // path (such as "Edit" and "Delete") when a node is being rendered outside
  59   // of its own page (for example, when a teaser of the node is being displayed
  60   // on the front page of the site), you only need to inform Drupal's menu
  61   // system that your path is a contextual link also, and it will automatically
  62   // appear with the others. In the example below, we add a contextual link
  63   // named "Example action" to the list.
  64   $items['node/%node/example-action'] = array(
  65     'title' => 'Example action',
  66     'page callback' => 'drupal_get_form',
  67     'page arguments' => array('contextual_links_example_node_action_form', 1),
  68     'access callback' => TRUE,
  69     // To be displayed as a contextual link, a menu item should be defined as
  70     // one of the node's local tasks.
  71     'type' => MENU_LOCAL_TASK,
  72     // To make the local task display as a contextual link, specify the
  73     // optional 'context' argument. The most common method is to set both
  74     // MENU_CONTEXT_PAGE and MENU_CONTEXT_INLINE (shown below), which causes
  75     // the link to display as both a tab on the node page and as an entry in
  76     // the contextual links dropdown. This is recommended for most cases
  77     // because not all users who have permission to visit the "Example action"
  78     // page will necessarily have access to contextual links, and they still
  79     // need a way to get to the page via the user interface.
  80     'context' => MENU_CONTEXT_PAGE | MENU_CONTEXT_INLINE,
  81     // If we give the item a large weight, we can make it display as the last
  82     // tab on the page, as well as the last item inside the contextual links
  83     // dropdown.
  84     'weight' => 80,
  85   );
  86 
  87   // Second example (attaching contextual links to a block):
  88   //
  89   // If your module provides content that is displayed in a block, you can
  90   // attach contextual links to the block that allow actions to be performed on
  91   // it. This is useful for administrative pages that affect the content
  92   // wherever it is displayed or used on the site. For configuration options
  93   // that only affect the appearance of the content in the block itself, it is
  94   // better to implement hook_block_configure() rather than creating a separate
  95   // administrative page (this allows your options to appear when an
  96   // administrator clicks the existing "Configure block" contextual link
  97   // already provided by the Block module).
  98   //
  99   // In the code below, we assume that your module has a type of object
 100   // ("contextual links example object") that will be displayed in a block. The
 101   // code below defines menu items for this object using a standard pattern,
 102   // with "View" and "Edit object" as the object's local tasks, and makes the
 103   // "Edit object" item display as a contextual link in addition to a tab. Once
 104   // the contextual links are defined here, additional steps are required to
 105   // actually display the content in a block and attach the contextual links to
 106   // the block itself. This occurs in contextual_links_example_block_info() and
 107   // contextual_links_example_block_view().
 108   $items['examples/contextual-links/%contextual_links_example_object'] = array(
 109     'title' => 'Contextual links example object',
 110     'page callback' => 'contextual_links_example_object_page',
 111     'page arguments' => array(2),
 112     'access callback' => TRUE,
 113   );
 114   $items['examples/contextual-links/%contextual_links_example_object/view'] = array(
 115     'title' => 'View',
 116     'type' => MENU_DEFAULT_LOCAL_TASK,
 117     'weight' => -10,
 118   );
 119   $items['examples/contextual-links/%contextual_links_example_object/edit'] = array(
 120     'title' => 'Edit object',
 121     'page callback' => 'drupal_get_form',
 122     'page arguments' => array('contextual_links_example_object_edit_form', 2),
 123     'access callback' => TRUE,
 124     'type' => MENU_LOCAL_TASK,
 125     // As in our first example, this is the line of code that makes "Edit
 126     // "object" display as a contextual link in addition to as a tab.
 127     'context' => MENU_CONTEXT_PAGE | MENU_CONTEXT_INLINE,
 128   );
 129 
 130   // Third example (attaching contextual links directly to your module's
 131   // content):
 132   //
 133   // Sometimes your module may want to display its content in an arbitrary
 134   // location and attach contextual links there. For example, you might
 135   // display your content in a listing on its own page and then attach the
 136   // contextual links directly to each piece of content in the listing. Here,
 137   // we will reuse the menu items and contextual links that were defined for
 138   // our example object above, and display them in a listing in
 139   // contextual_links_overview_page().
 140   $items['examples/contextual-links'] = array(
 141     'title' => 'Contextual Links Example',
 142     'page callback' => 'contextual_links_overview_page',
 143     'access callback' => TRUE,
 144   );
 145 
 146   return $items;
 147 }
 148 
 149 /**
 150  * Menu loader callback for the object defined by this module.
 151  *
 152  * @param $id
 153  *   The ID of the object to load.
 154  *
 155  * @return
 156  *   A fully loaded object, or FALSE if the object does not exist.
 157  */
 158 function contextual_links_example_object_load($id) {
 159   // In a real use case, this function might load an object from the database.
 160   // For the sake of this example, we just define a stub object with a basic
 161   // title and content for any numeric ID that is passed in.
 162   if (is_numeric($id)) {
 163     $object = new stdClass();
 164     $object->id = $id;
 165     $object->title = t('Title for example object @id', array('@id' => $id));
 166     $object->content = t('This is the content of example object @id.', array('@id' => $id));
 167     return $object;
 168   }
 169   else {
 170     return FALSE;
 171   }
 172 }
 173 
 174 /**
 175  * Implements hook_block_info().
 176  */
 177 function contextual_links_example_block_info() {
 178   // Define the block that will display our module's content.
 179   $blocks['example']['info'] = t('Contextual links example block');
 180   return $blocks;
 181 }
 182 
 183 /**
 184  * Implements hook_block_view().
 185  */
 186 function contextual_links_example_block_view($delta = '') {
 187   if ($delta == 'example') {
 188     // Display our module's content inside a block. In a real use case, we
 189     // might define a new block for each object that exists. For the sake of
 190     // this example, though, we only define one block and hardcode it to always
 191     // display object #1.
 192     $id = 1;
 193     $object = contextual_links_example_object_load($id);
 194     $block['subject'] = t('Contextual links example block for object @id', array('@id' => $id));
 195     $block['content'] = array(
 196       // In order to attach contextual links, the block's content must be a
 197       // renderable array. (Normally this would involve themed output using
 198       // #theme, but for simplicity we just use HTML markup directly here.)
 199       '#type' => 'markup',
 200       '#markup' => filter_xss($object->content),
 201       // Contextual links are attached to the block array using the special
 202       // #contextual_links property. The #contextual_links property contains an
 203       // array, keyed by the name of each module that is attaching contextual
 204       // links to it.
 205       '#contextual_links' => array(
 206         'contextual_links_example' => array(
 207           // Each element is itself an array, containing two elements which are
 208           // combined together to form the base path whose contextual links
 209           // should be attached. The two elements are split such that the first
 210           // is the static part of the path and the second is the dynamic part.
 211           // (This split is for performance reasons.) For example, the code
 212           // below tells Drupal to load the menu item corresponding to the path
 213           // "examples/contextual-links/$id" and attach all this item's
 214           // contextual links (which were defined in hook_menu()) to the object
 215           // when it is rendered. If the contextual links you are attaching
 216           // don't have any dynamic elements in their path, you can pass an
 217           // empty array as the second element.
 218           'examples/contextual-links',
 219           array($id),
 220         ),
 221       ),
 222     );
 223     // Since we are attaching our contextual links to a block, and the Block
 224     // module takes care of rendering the block in such a way that contextual
 225     // links are supported, we do not need to do anything else here. When the
 226     // appropriate conditions are met, the contextual links we have defined
 227     // will automatically appear attached to the block, next to the "Configure
 228     // block" link that the Block module itself provides.
 229     return $block;
 230   }
 231 }
 232 
 233 /**
 234  * Menu callback; displays a listing of objects defined by this module.
 235  *
 236  * @see contextual_links_example_theme()
 237  * @see contextual-links-example-object.tpl.php
 238  * @see contextual_links_example_block_view()
 239  */
 240 function contextual_links_overview_page() {
 241   $build = array();
 242 
 243   // For simplicity, we will hardcode this example page to list five of our
 244   // module's objects.
 245   for ($id = 1; $id <= 5; $id++) {
 246     $object = contextual_links_example_object_load($id);
 247     $build[$id] = array(
 248       // To support attaching contextual links to an object that we are
 249       // displaying on our own, the object must be themed in a particular way.
 250       // See contextual_links_example_theme() and
 251       // contextual-links-example-object.tpl.php for more discussion.
 252       '#theme' => 'contextual_links_example_object',
 253       '#object' => $object,
 254       // Contextual links are attached to the block using the special
 255       // #contextual_links property. See contextual_links_example_block_view()
 256       // for discussion of the syntax used here.
 257       '#contextual_links' => array(
 258         'contextual_links_example' => array(
 259           'examples/contextual-links',
 260           array($id),
 261         ),
 262       ),
 263     );
 264   }
 265 
 266   return $build;
 267 }
 268 
 269 /**
 270  * Implements hook_theme().
 271  *
 272  * @see template_preprocess_contextual_links_example_object()
 273  */
 274 function contextual_links_example_theme() {
 275   // The core Contextual Links module imposes two restrictions on how an object
 276   // must be themed in order for it to display the object's contextual links in
 277   // the user interface:
 278   // - The object must use a template file rather than a theme function. See
 279   //   contextual-links-example-object.tpl.php for more information on how the
 280   //   template file should be structured.
 281   // - The first variable passed to the template must be a renderable array. In
 282   //   this case, we accomplish that via the most common method, by passing a
 283   //   single renderable element.
 284   return array(
 285     'contextual_links_example_object' => array(
 286       'template' => 'contextual-links-example-object',
 287       'render element' => 'element',
 288     ),
 289   );
 290 }
 291 
 292 /**
 293  * Process variables for contextual-links-example-object.tpl.php.
 294  *
 295  * @see contextual_links_overview_page()
 296  */
 297 function template_preprocess_contextual_links_example_object(&$variables) {
 298   // Here we take the object that is being themed and define some useful
 299   // variables that we will print in the template file.
 300   $variables['title'] = filter_xss($variables['element']['#object']->title);
 301   $variables['content'] = filter_xss($variables['element']['#object']->content);
 302 }
 303 
 304 /**
 305  * Menu callback; displays an object defined by this module on its own page.
 306  *
 307  * @see contextual_links_overview_page()
 308  */
 309 function contextual_links_example_object_page($object) {
 310   // Here we render the object but without the #contextual_links property,
 311   // since we don't want contextual links to appear when the object is already
 312   // being displayed on its own page.
 313   $build = array(
 314     '#theme' => 'contextual_links_example_object',
 315     '#object' => $object,
 316   );
 317 
 318   return $build;
 319 }
 320 
 321 /**
 322  * Form callback; display the form for editing our module's content.
 323  *
 324  * @ingroup forms
 325  * @see contextual_links_example_object_edit_form_submit()
 326  */
 327 function contextual_links_example_object_edit_form($form, &$form_state, $object) {
 328   $form['text'] = array(
 329     '#markup' => t('This is the page that would allow you to edit object @id.', array('@id' => $object->id)),
 330     '#prefix' => '<p>',
 331     '#suffix' => '</p>',
 332   );
 333   $form['object_id'] = array(
 334     '#type' => 'value',
 335     '#value' => $object->id,
 336   );
 337 
 338   $form['actions'] = array('#type' => 'actions');
 339   $form['actions']['submit'] = array(
 340     '#type' => 'submit',
 341     '#value' => t('Submit'),
 342   );
 343 
 344   return $form;
 345 }
 346 
 347 /**
 348  * Submit handler for contextual_links_example_object_edit_form().
 349  */
 350 function contextual_links_example_object_edit_form_submit($form, &$form_state) {
 351   drupal_set_message(t('Object @id was edited.', array('@id' => $form_state['values']['object_id'])));
 352 }
 353 
 354 /**
 355  * Form callback; display the form for performing an example action on a node.
 356  *
 357  * @ingroup forms
 358  * @see contextual_links_example_node_action_form_submit()
 359  */
 360 function contextual_links_example_node_action_form($form, &$form_state, $node) {
 361   $form['text'] = array(
 362     '#markup' => t('This is the page that would allow you to perform an example action on node @nid.', array('@nid' => $node->nid)),
 363     '#prefix' => '<p>',
 364     '#suffix' => '</p>',
 365   );
 366   $form['nid'] = array(
 367     '#type' => 'value',
 368     '#value' => $node->nid,
 369   );
 370 
 371   $form['actions'] = array('#type' => 'actions');
 372   $form['actions']['submit'] = array(
 373     '#type' => 'submit',
 374     '#value' => t('Submit'),
 375   );
 376 
 377   return $form;
 378 }
 379 
 380 /**
 381  * Submit handler for contextual_links_example_node_action_form().
 382  */
 383 function contextual_links_example_node_action_form_submit($form, &$form_state) {
 384   drupal_set_message(t('The example action was performed on node @nid.', array('@nid' => $form_state['values']['nid'])));
 385 }
 386 /**
 387  * @} End of "defgroup contextual_links_example".
 388  */

contextual_links_example.test

  1 <?php
   2 
   3 /**
   4  * @file
   5  * Functional tests for the contextual_links_example module.
   6  */
   7 
   8 /**
   9  * Functional tests for the contextual_links_example module.
  10  *
  11  * @ingroup contextual_links_example
  12  */
  13 class ContextualLinksExampleTestCase extends DrupalWebTestCase {
  14   protected $web_user;
  15 
  16   public static function getInfo() {
  17     return array(
  18       'name' => 'Contextual links example functionality',
  19       'description' => 'Tests the behavior of the contextual links provided by the Contextual links example module.',
  20       'group' => 'Examples',
  21     );
  22   }
  23 
  24   /**
  25    * Enable modules and create user with specific permissions.
  26    */
  27   public function setUp() {
  28     parent::setUp('contextual', 'contextual_links_example');
  29     $this->web_user = $this->drupalCreateUser(array('access contextual links', 'administer blocks'));
  30     $this->drupalLogin($this->web_user);
  31   }
  32 
  33   /**
  34    * Test the various contextual links that this module defines and displays.
  35    */
  36   function testContextualLinksExample() {
  37     // Create a node and promote it to the front page. Then view the front page
  38     // and verify that the "Example action" contextual link works.
  39     $node = $this->drupalCreateNode(array('type' => 'page', 'promote' => 1));
  40     $this->drupalGet('');
  41     $this->clickLink(t('Example action'));
  42     $this->assertUrl('node/' . $node->nid . '/example-action', array('query' => array('destination' => 'node')));
  43 
  44     // Visit our example overview page and click the third contextual link.
  45     // This should take us to a page for editing the third object we defined.
  46     $this->drupalGet('examples/contextual-links');
  47     $this->clickLink('Edit object', 2);
  48     $this->assertUrl('examples/contextual-links/3/edit', array('query' => array('destination' => 'examples/contextual-links')));
  49 
  50     // Enable our module's block, go back to the front page, and click the
  51     // "Edit object" contextual link that we expect to be there.
  52     $edit['blocks[contextual_links_example_example][region]'] = 'sidebar_first';
  53     $this->drupalPost('admin/structure/block', $edit, t('Save blocks'));
  54     $this->drupalGet('');
  55     $this->clickLink('Edit object');
  56     $this->assertUrl('examples/contextual-links/1/edit', array('query' => array('destination' => 'node')));
  57   }
  58 }